<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon vpon the eighth verse of the first chapter of the Acts of the Apostles Preached to the Honourable Company of the Virginian Plantation, 13. Nouemb. 1622. By Iohn Donne Deane of Saint Pauls, London.</title>
            <title>Sermon upon the viii. verse of the I. chapter of the Acts of the Apostles</title>
            <author>Donne, John, 1572-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109974</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898417</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898417</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73849)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2061:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon vpon the eighth verse of the first chapter of the Acts of the Apostles Preached to the Honourable Company of the Virginian Plantation, 13. Nouemb. 1622. By Iohn Donne Deane of Saint Pauls, London.</title>
                  <title>Sermon upon the viii. verse of the I. chapter of the Acts of the Apostles</title>
                  <author>Donne, John, 1572-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed [by Bernard Alsop] for Thomas Iones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant: quire A in an earlier setting; title has "eight vere". Most copies have pages A3v and A4r transposed.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of "Foure sermons upon speciall occasions" and "Five sermons upon speciall occasions".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts I, 8 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132980:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132980:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON VPON THE EIGHTH VERSE OF THE FIRST CHAPTER OF THE ACTS OF THE APOSTLES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached</hi> To the Honourable Company of the VIRGINIAN PLANTATION, 13. <hi>Nouemb.</hi> 1622.</p>
            <p>BY IOHN DONNE Deane of Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Thomas Iones.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:132980:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132980:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE COMPANIE OF THE VIRGINIAN PLAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y your Fauours, I had ſome place amongst you, before; but now I am an <hi>Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer,</hi> if not to <hi>VIRGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA,</hi> yet for <hi>VIRGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA:</hi> for, euery man that <hi>Prints, Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> For the <hi>Preaching</hi> of this <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> I was but vnder your <hi>Inuitation;</hi> my <hi>Time</hi> was mine owne, and my <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> mine owne: and I had beene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable towards you, if I had turned that <hi>Time,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Meditations,</hi> to <hi>GODS</hi> Seruice, in any other place. But for the <hi>Printing</hi> of this <hi>Sermon,</hi> I am not onely vnder your <hi>Inuitation,</hi> but vnder your
<pb facs="tcp:132980:3"/>
               <hi>Commandement;</hi> for, after it was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, it was not mine, but yours: And therefore, if I gaue it at firſt, I doe but restore it now. The firſt, was an act of <hi>Loue;</hi> this, of <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> both which <hi>Vertues, Almightie God</hi> euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more promoue, and exalt in all your proceedings. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Seruant in Chriſt Ieſus, IOHN DONNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132980:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ACTS 1.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But yee ſhall receiue power after that the <hi>HOLY GHOST</hi> is come vpon you, and yee ſhall be witneſſes vnto mee both in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and in all <hi>Iudea,</hi> and in <hi>Samaria,</hi> and vnto the vttermoſt part of the Earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are reckoned in this Booke, Two and Twentie <hi>Sermons</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and yet the Book is not called the <hi>Preaching,</hi> but the <hi>Practiſe,</hi> not the <hi>Words,</hi> but the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> and the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were to conuey that name of <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> and to propagate
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132980:4"/>his <hi>Goſpell</hi> ouer all the world: Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, you are <hi>Actors</hi> vpon the ſame Stage too: the vttermoſt part of the Earth are your <hi>Scene:</hi> Act ouer the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> bee you a Light to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that ſit in darkeneſſe; bee you content to carrie him ouer theſe <hi>Seas,</hi> who dryed vp one <hi>Red Sea</hi> for his firſt people, and hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out another <hi>Red Sea,</hi> his owne Bloud, for them and vs. When man was fallen, <hi>God</hi> cloathed him, made him a Leather Garment; there <hi>God</hi> deſcended to one Occupation: when the time of mans Redemption was come, then <hi>God,</hi> as it were, to houſe him, became a <hi>Carpenters Sonne,</hi> there <hi>God</hi> deſcended to another Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Naturally, without doubt, man would haue beene his owne Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and his owne Carpenter; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in theſe two kinds man would haue done of himſelfe, though hee had had no patterne from <hi>God:</hi> but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132980:4"/>in preſeruing man who was fallen, to this redemption, by which he was to be raiſd, in preſeruing man from peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, in the Flood, <hi>God</hi> deſcended to a third occupation, to be his <hi>Shipwright</hi> to giue him the modell of a Ship, an <hi>Arke,</hi> and ſo to be the author of that, which man himſelfe in likelihood, would neuer haue thought of, a means to paſſe from <hi>Nation</hi> to <hi>Nation.</hi> Now, as <hi>GOD</hi> taught vs to make cloathes, not onely to cloath our ſelues, but to cloath him in his poore and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked members heere; as <hi>God</hi> taught vs to build houſes, not to houſe our ſelues, but to houſe him, in erecting <hi>Churches,</hi> to his glory: So <hi>God</hi> taught vs to make Ships, not to tranſport our ſelues, but to tranſport him, <hi>That when wee haue receiued power, after that the Holy Ghoſt is come vpon vs, we might be witneſſes vnto him, both in</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Iudaea, <hi>and in</hi> Samaria, <hi>and vnto the vttermoſt parts of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:132980:5"/>As I ſpeake now principally to them who are concernd in this <hi>Plantation</hi> of <hi>Virginia,</hi> yet there may be diuers in this Congregation, who, though they haue no intereſt in this <hi>Plantation,</hi> yet they may haue benefit and edification, by that which they heare me ſay, ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpoke the words of this <hi>Text,</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who were preſent and queſtioned him at his <hi>Aſcention,</hi> but they are in their iuſt extention, and due accomodation, appliable to our preſent occation of meeting heere: As <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe is <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> ſo firſt, as that hee is laſt too, ſo theſe wordes which he ſpoke in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to vs, who are to glorifie him in the <hi>Weſt? That we hauing receiued pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, after that the</hi> Holy Ghoſt <hi>is come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, might be witneſſes vnto him, both in</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Iudea, <hi>and in</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, <hi>and vnto the vttermoſt parts of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt word of the Text is the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132980:5"/>
               <hi>Cardinall</hi> word, the word the <hi>hinge</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the whole <hi>Text</hi> turnes; The firſt word, <hi>But,</hi> is the <hi>But,</hi> that all the reſt ſhoots at. Firſt it is an <hi>excluſiue</hi> word; ſomething the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, which might not bee had; not that; And it is an <hi>incluſiue</hi> word; ſomthing <hi>Chriſt</hi> was pleaſd to affoord to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> which they thought not of; not that, not that which you beat vpon, <hi>But,</hi> but yet, ſomething elſe, ſomething better then that, you ſhall haue. That which this but, <hi>excludes,</hi> is that which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> expreſſe in the <hi>Verſe</hi> immediatly before the <hi>Text, a Temporall Kingdome; Wilt thou reſtore againe the kingdome of Iſrael?</hi> No; not a temporall Kingdome; let not the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and commodities of this world, be in your contemplation in your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures. Or, becauſe they aske more, <hi>Wilt thou now reſtore that?</hi> not yet: If I will giue you riches, and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of this world, yet if I doe it not at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132980:6"/>firſt, if I doe it not yet, be not you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged; you ſhall not haue <hi>that,</hi> that is not <hi>Gods</hi> firſt intention; and though that be in Gods intention, to giue it you hereafter, you ſhall not haue it yet; thats the <hi>excluſiue</hi> part; <hi>But;</hi> there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the <hi>incluſiue, You ſhall receiue power, after that the Holy Ghoſt is come vpon you, and you ſhall bee witneſſes vnto mee, both in</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Iudaea, <hi>and in</hi> Samaria, <hi>and vnto the vttermoſt parts of the Earth.</hi> In which ſecond part, we ſhall paſſe by theſe ſteps; <hi>Superueniet Spiritus,</hi> The <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> ſhall come vpon you, <hi>The Spirit</hi> ſhall witneſſe to <hi>your Spirit,</hi> and rectifie your Conſcience; And then, by that, you ſhall receiue <hi>power;</hi> A new power beſides the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er you haue from the <hi>State,</hi> and that power ſhall enable you, to be witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is, to make his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine the more credible, by your teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, when you conforme your ſelues to him, and doe as hee did; and this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132980:6"/>witneſſe you ſhall beare, this confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity you ſhall declare, firſt in <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> in this <hi>Citie;</hi> And in <hi>Iudaea,</hi> in all the parts of the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> and in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> euen amongſt them who are departed from the true worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and to the vttermoſt part of the Earth, to thoſe poore <hi>Soules,</hi> to whom you are continually ſending. Summarily, If from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> you haue a good teſtimony in your owne Conſcience, you ſhall be witneſſes for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is, as he did, you ſhall giue ſatisfaction to all, to the <hi>Citie,</hi> to the <hi>Countrey,</hi> to the <hi>Calumniating Aduerſary,</hi> and the naturals of the place, to whom you ſhall preſent both <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>Temporall</hi> benefit to. And ſo you haue the <hi>Modell</hi> of the whole frame, and of the partitions; wee proceede now to the furniſhing of the particular roomes.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:132980:7"/>
               <head>1. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt then, this firſt word, <hi>But,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes a temporall Kingdome; the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had fild themſelues with an expectation, with an ambition of it; but that was not intended them. It was no wonder, that a woman could conceiue ſuch an expectation, and ſuch an ambition, as to haue her two ſonnes ſit at <hi>Chriſts</hi> right hand,
<note place="margin">Mat. 20.20.</note> and at his left, in his Kingdome, when the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> expected ſuch a Kingdome, as might affoord them honours and preferment vpon Earth. More then once they were in the diſputation, in which <hi>Chriſt</hi> deprehended them,
<note place="margin">Mat. 1.81.</note> 
                  <hi>which of them ſhould bee the greateſt in his Kingdome.</hi> Neither hath the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> any thing, wherein he may ſo properly call himſelfe <hi>Apoſt licall,</hi> as this error of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> this theire infirmitie; that heis euermore too conuerſant vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132980:7"/>of temporall Kingdomes. They did it all the way, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was with them, and now at his laſt ſtep, <hi>Cum actu aſcendiſſet,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not <hi>Aſending,</hi> but in part <hi>aſcended,</hi> when one foot was vpon the Earth, and the other in the cloud that tooke him vp, they aske him now, wilt thou at this time, reſtore the Kingdome? ſo women put their husbands, and men their fathers, and friends, vpon their torture, at their laſt gaſpe, and make their death- bed a racke to make them ſtrech and encreaſe ioyntures, and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and legacies, and ſigne Scedules and Codicils, with their hand, when his hand that preſents them is ready to cloſe his eyes, that ſhould ſigne them: And when they are vpon the wing for heauen, men tye lead to their feet, and when they are laying hand faſt vpon <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, they muſt pull their hand out of his boſome againe, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey importunities of men, and ſigne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132980:8"/>their papers: ſo vnderminable is the loue of this World, which determines euery minute. <hi>GOD,</hi> as hee is three perſons, hath three Kingdomes; There is <hi>Regnum potentiae,</hi> The Kingdome of power; and this wee attribute to the <hi>Father;</hi> it is power and prouidence: There is <hi>Regnum gloriae,</hi> the Kingdome of glorie; this we attribute to the <hi>Sonn</hi> and to his purchaſe; for he is <hi>the King</hi> that ſhall ſay,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Come ye bloſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you, from the foundation of the World.</hi> And then betweene theſe three is <hi>Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Gratiae,</hi> The Kingdome of Grace, and this weattribute to the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> he takes them, whom the king of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, Almighty <hi>God</hi> hath reſcued from the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and as the king of grace, <hi>Hee giues them the knowledge of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the Kingdome of</hi> GOD,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.11.</note> that is, of <hi>future glory,</hi> by ſanctifying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his grace, in his <hi>Church.</hi> The two firſt kingdomes are in this world, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132980:8"/>yet neither of them, are of this world; becauſe both they referre to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory. The kingdome of the <hi>Father,</hi> which is the prouidence of <hi>God,</hi> does but preſerue vs; The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> which is the grace of <hi>God,</hi> does but prepare vs to the kingdome of the <hi>Sonne,</hi> which is the glory of <hi>GOD;</hi> and thats in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And therfore, though to good men, this world be the way to that kingdome, yet this kingdome is not of this world, ſayes Chiſt himſelfe: Though the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelues,
<note place="margin">Iohn 18.36.</note> as good a <hi>Schoole</hi> as they were bred in, could neuer take out that leſſon yet that leſſon <hi>Chriſt</hi> giues, and repeates to all, you ſeeke a Temporall kingdome, <hi>But,</hi> ſayes the Text, ſtop there, A king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome you muſt not haue.</p>
               <p>Beloued in him, whoſe kingdome, and Goſpell you ſeeke to aduance, in this Plantation, our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Sauiour Christ Ieſus,</hi> if you ſeeke to eſtabliſh a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132980:9"/>temporall kingdome there, you are not rectified, if you ſeeke to bee <hi>kings</hi> in either acceptation of the word; To be a <hi>King</hi> ſignifies <hi>Libertie</hi> and <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pency,</hi> and <hi>Supremacie,</hi> to bee vnder no man, and to be a <hi>King</hi> ſignifies <hi>Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,</hi> and <hi>Omniſufficiencie,</hi> to neede no man. If thoſe that gouerne there, would eſtabliſh ſuch a gouernment, as ſhould not depend vpon this, or if thoſe that goe thither, propoſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues an exemption from Lawes, to liue at their libertie, this is to be <hi>Kings,</hi> to deueſt <hi>Allegeance,</hi> to bee vnder no man: and if thoſe that aduenture thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, propoſe to themſelues preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and profit, a ſodaine way to bee rich, and an aboundance of all deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble commodities from thence, this is to be ſufficient of themſelues, and to neede no man: and to bee vnder no man and to neede no man, are the two acceptations of being <hi>Kings.</hi> Whom li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty drawes to goe, or preſent profit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132980:9"/>drawes to aduenture, are not yet in the right way. O, if you could once bring a <hi>Catechiſme</hi> to bee as good ware a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them as a Bugle, as a knife, as a hatchet: O, if you would bee as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to hearken at the returne of a <hi>ſhip,</hi> how many <hi>Indians</hi> were conuerted to <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> as what trees, or druggs, or Dyes that Ship had brought, then you were in your right way, and not till then; <hi>Libertie</hi> and <hi>Abundance,</hi> are Characters of kingdomes, and a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is excluded in the <hi>Text;</hi> The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> were not to looke for it, in their employment, nor you in this your Plantation.</p>
               <p>At leaſt CHRIST expreſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thus farre, in this anſwer, that if he would giue them a kingdome,
<note place="margin">Non adhue.</note> hee would not giue it them yet. They aske him, <hi>Wilt thou at this time, reſtore the kingdome?</hi> and hee anſwers, <hi>It is not for you to know the times:</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <hi>God</hi> will doe, Man muſt not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132980:10"/>appoint him his time. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> thought of a <hi>kingdome</hi> preſently after <hi>Chriſts</hi> departure; the comming of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> who lead them into all truthes, ſoone deliuered them of that error. Other men in fauour of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> interpreting all the propheſies, which are of a <hi>Spirituall Kingdome,</hi> the kingdome of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> into which, the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhall be admitted) in a literall ſenſe, haue thought that the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhall haue, not onely a temporall kingdome in the ſame place, in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> againe, but becauſe they finde that kingdome which is promiſed, (that is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Goſpell</hi>) to bee expreſſed in large phraſes, and in an abundant manner, applying all that largeneſſe to a temporall kingdome, they thinke, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhall haue ſuch a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as ſhall ſwallow and annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late all other kingdomes, and bee the ſole <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the world. After this, very great men in the <hi>Church</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:132980:10"/>vpon theſe words, of One thouſand yeares after the Reſurrection, haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin'd a <hi>Temporall Kingdome</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God</hi> heere vpon Earth,
<note place="margin">Apo. 20.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they entred the ioyes of Heauen: and Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Ciuit. Dei</hi> 20.7.</note> had at firſt ſome declinations towards that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, though he diſpute powerfully againſt it, after: That there ſhould bee <hi>Sabatiſmus in terris;</hi> that as the world was to laſt Sixe thouſand yeares in troubles, there ſhould be a Seuenth thouſand, in ſuch ioyes as this world could giue.</p>
               <p>And ſome others, who haue auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both the <hi>Temporall kingdome</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd by the <hi>Apostles,</hi> preſently after the <hi>Aſcention,</hi> And the <hi>Emperiall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> before the <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> And the <hi>Carnall kingdome</hi> of the <hi>Chiliasts,</hi> the <hi>Millenarians,</hi> after the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> though they ſpeake of no kingdome, but the true kingdome, the kingdome of glory, yet they erre as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132980:11"/>much in aſsigning a certaine time when that kingdome ſhall beginne, when the ende of this world, when the Reſurrection, when the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be. <hi>Non eſt vestrum noſſe tempora,</hi> ſayes <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> then; and leſt it might be thought, that they might know theſe things, when the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> came vpon them, <hi>Chriſt</hi> denies that he himſelfe knew that, as <hi>Man;</hi> and as <hi>Man, Chriſt</hi> knew more, then euer the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> knew. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> intended to his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> heere, hee would not giue it preſently, <hi>non adhuc,</hi> hee would not binde himſelfe to a certaine time, <hi>Non eſt veſtrum noſſe tempora,</hi> It belongs not to vs to know <hi>Gods</hi> times.</p>
               <p>Beloued, vſe godly means, and giue <hi>God</hi> his leiſure. You cannot beget a Sonne, and tell the Mother, I will haue this Sonne born within fiue Moneths; nor, when he is borne, ſay, you will haue him paſt daunger of <hi>Wardſhip</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:132980:11"/>within fiue yeares. You cannot ſowe your Corne to day, and ſay it ſhall bee aboue ground to morrow, and in my Barne next weeke. How ſoone the beſt Husbandman, ſow'd the beſt Seede in the beſt ground? GOD caſt the promiſe of a <hi>Meſsias,</hi> as the ſeede of all, in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; <hi>In Semine Mulieris; The Seede of the Woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head;</hi> and yet this <hi>Plant</hi> was Foure thouſand yeares after before it appeared; this <hi>Meſsias</hi> Foure thouſand yeares before he came. <hi>GOD</hi> ſhew'd the ground where that ſhould grow, Two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares after the Promiſe; in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Family; <hi>In ſemine tuo, In thy Seed all Nations ſhall be bleſſed. God</hi> hedg'd in this Ground almoſt One thouſand yeares after that; In <hi>Micheas</hi> time, <hi>Et tu Bethlem, Thou Bethlem ſhalt bee the place;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> watered that, and wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that, refreſhed that dry expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with a Succeſſion of <hi>Prophets;</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:132980:12"/>yet it was ſo long before this <hi>expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Nations,</hi> this <hi>Meſsias</hi> came. So GOD promiſed the <hi>Iewes</hi> a Kingdome, in <hi>Iacobs</hi> Prophecie to <hi>Iuda,
<note place="margin">Gen. 49.</note> That the Scepter ſhould not depart from his Tribe.</hi> In Two hundred yeares more, he ſaies no more of it;
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.14.</note> then he ordaines ſome inſtitutions for their <hi>King,</hi> when they ſhould haue one. And then it was Foure hundred yeares after that, before they had a <hi>King.</hi> GOD meant from the firſt houre, to people the whole earth; and <hi>God</hi> could haue made men of clay, as faſt as they made Brickes of Clay in <hi>Egypt;</hi> but he began vpon two, and when they had beene multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying and repleniſhing the Earth One thouſand ſixe hundred yeares, the <hi>Flood</hi> waſhed all that away, and GOD was almoſt to begin againe vpon eight perſons; and they haue ſeru'd to peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Heauen</hi> too; Bee not you diſcouraged, if the Promiſes which you haue made to your ſelues,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132980:12"/>or to others, be not ſo ſoone diſcharg'd; though you ſee not your money, though you ſee not your men, though a <hi>Flood,</hi> a <hi>Flood</hi> of <hi>Bloud</hi> haue broken in vpon them, be not diſcouraged. Great Creatures lye long in the Wombe; <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are litterd perfit, but <hi>Beare-whelpes</hi> lick'd vnto their ſhape; actions which Kings vndertake, are caſt in a mould, they haue their perfection quickly; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of priuate men; and priuate Purſes, require more hammering, and more filing to their perfection. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let your principall end, be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the <hi>glorious Goſpell:</hi> and though there bee an <hi>Excluſiue</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> GOD does not promiſe you a <hi>Kingdome, Eaſe,</hi> and <hi>Abundance</hi> in all things, and that which hee does intend to you, he does not promiſe preſently, yet there is an <hi>Incluſiue</hi> too; not that, <hi>But,</hi> but ſomething equiuolent at leaſt, <hi>But yee ſhall receiue power, after that the Holy Ghoſt is come vpon you, and yee ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132980:13"/>be witneſſes vnto me, both in</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Iudaea, <hi>and in</hi> Samaria, <hi>and vnto the vttermoſt parts of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> does not ſay to theſe men, ſince you are ſo importunate, you ſhall haue <hi>no Kingdome; now,</hi> nor <hi>neuer,</hi> tis, <hi>not yet; But,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sed.</note> hee does not ſay, you ſhall haue <hi>no Kingdome, nor any thing elſe,</hi> tis, <hi>not that; But:</hi> the importunitie of beggers, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times drawes vs to ſuch a froward an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, For this importunitie, I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer giue you any thing. Our patterne was not ſo froward; hee gaue them not that, but as good as that. <hi>Samuel</hi> was ſent to ſuper-induct a <hi>King</hi> vpon <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> to annoint a new King. Hee thought his <hi>Commiſsion</hi> had been deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in <hi>Eliab, Surely this is the Lords Annointed.</hi> But the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid, not hee;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132980:13"/>nor the next, <hi>Aminadab;</hi> nor the next, <hi>Shammah;</hi> nor none of the next ſeuen; <hi>But;</hi> but yet there is one in the field, keeping ſheepe, annoint him; <hi>Dauid</hi> is hee. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prayed earneſtly, and frequently, to be diſcharged of that <hi>Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulas Carnis: God</hi> ſayes no; <hi>not that;</hi> but <hi>Gratia mea ſufficit,</hi> Thou ſhalt haue grace to ouercome the tentation, though the tentation remaine. <hi>God</hi> ſayes to you, <hi>No Kingdome,</hi> not <hi>Eaſe,</hi> not <hi>Abundance;</hi> nay, <hi>nothing at all yet;</hi> the Plantation ſhall not diſcharge the Charges, not defray it ſelfe yet; but yet alreadie, now at firſt, it ſhall conduce to great vſes: It ſhall redeeme many a wretch from the Lawes of death, from the hands of the Executioner, vpon whom, perchance a ſmall fault, or perchance a firſt fault, or perchance a fault heartily and ſincerely repented, perchance no fault, but mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, had otherwiſe caſt a preſent and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious death. It ſhall ſweepe your ſtreetes, and waſh your doores, from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:132980:14"/>idle perſons, and the children of idle perſons, and imploy them: and truely, if the whole Countrey were but ſuch a <hi>Bridewell,</hi> to force idle perſons to work, it had a good vſe. But it is alreadie, not onely a <hi>Spleene,</hi> to drayne the ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of the body, but a <hi>Liuer,</hi> to breed good bloud; alreadie the imployment breedes Marriners; alreadie the place giues Eſſayes, nay, Fraights of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantable Commodities; alreadie it is a marke for the Enuie, and for the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of our Enemies; I ſpeake but of our <hi>Doctrinall,</hi> not <hi>Nationall</hi> Enemies: as they are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> they are ſorrie wee haue this Countrey; and ſurely, twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lectures in matter of Controuerſie doe not ſo much vexe them, as one Ship that goes, and ſtrengthens that Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Neyther can I recommend it to you, by any better <hi>Rhetorique,</hi> then their mallice: They would gladly haue it, and therefore let vs be glad to hold it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:132980:14"/>Thus then this <hi>Text</hi> proceedes,
<note place="margin">Spiritus Sanctus.</note> and gathers vpon you. All that you would haue by this Plantation, you ſhall not haue: GOD bindes not himſelfe to meaſures; All that you ſhall haue, you haue not yet: GOD bindes not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to times, but ſomething you ſhall haue; nay, you haue alreadie ſome great things: and of thoſe, that in the <hi>Text</hi> is, <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſhall come vpon you.</hi> Wee finde the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> to haue come vpon men, foure times in this Booke: Firſt, vpon the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2, 1.</note> at <hi>Pentecost:</hi> Then, when the whole Congregation was in prayer for the impriſonment of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4, 31.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when <hi>Peter</hi> preached in <hi>Cornelius</hi> his houſe,
<note place="margin">10, 44.</note> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt fell vpon all them that heard him.</hi> And fourthly, when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> laid his hands vpon them,
<note place="margin">19, 6.</note> who had beene formerly bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> At the three latter times it is euident, that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> fell vpon whole and promiſcuous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:132980:15"/>Congregations, and not vpon the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> onely: and in the firſt, at <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> the contrarie is not euident; nay, the Fathers, for the moſt part, that handle that, concurre in that, that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> fell then vpon the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, men and women. The <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt</hi> fell vpon <hi>Peter</hi> before hee preach'd, and it fell vpon the hearers when hee preach'd, and it hath fallen vpon euery one of them, who haue found motions in themſelues, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> by this meanes. The <hi>Sonne of</hi> GOD did not abhorre the <hi>Virgins</hi> Wombe, when hee would be made man; when hee was man, hee did not diſdaine to ride vpon an <hi>Aſſe</hi> into <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> the third Perſon of the <hi>Trinitie,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> is as hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the ſecond, hee refuſes <hi>Nullum vehiculum,</hi> no conueyance, no doore of entrance into you; whether the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and precedent of other good men, or a probable imagination of future
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132980:15"/>profit, or a willingneſſe to concurre to the vexation of the Enemie; what col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterall reſpect ſoeuer drew thee in, if now thou art in, thy principall reſpect be the glorie of God; that occaſion, whatſoeuer it was, was <hi>vehiculum Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Sancti;</hi> that was the Petard, that broke open thy Iron Gate; that was the Chariot, by which he entred into thee, and now hee is fallen vpon thee, if thou doe not <hi>Depoſe;</hi> (lay aſide all conſideration of profit for euer, neuer to looke for returne) No, not <hi>Sepoſe,</hi> (leaue out the conſideration of profit for a time; for that, and Religion may well conſiſt together:) but if thou doe but <hi>Poſt-poſe</hi> the conſideration of Temporall gayne, and ſtudie firſt the aduancement of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> is fallen vpon you; for by that <hi>you receiue Power,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Text.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a <hi>Power</hi> rooted in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and a <hi>Power</hi> rooted in <hi>Grace;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Poteſtatem.</note> a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:132980:16"/>
                  <hi>Power</hi> iſſuing from the Law of <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and a <hi>Power</hi> growing out of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> In the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> A Land neuer inhabited by any, or vtterly derelicted, and immemori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally abandoned by the former Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, becomes theirs that will poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe it. So alſo is it, if the inhabitants doe not in ſome meaſure fill the Land, ſo as the Land may bring foorth her encreaſe for the vſe of men: for as a man does not become proprietarie of the Sea, becauſe hee hath two or three Boats fiſhing in it; ſo neyther does a man become Lord of a maine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, becauſe hee hath two or three Cottages in the Skirts thereof. That Rule which paſſes through all <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Lawes</hi> in particular States, <hi>Intereſt Reipublicae vt quis re ſua bene vtatur; The State muſt take order, that euerie man improoue that which he hath, for the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of that State,</hi> paſſes alſo through the Law of <hi>Nations,</hi> which is to all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132980:16"/>the World, as the <hi>Municipall</hi> Law is to a particular State: <hi>Intereſt Mundo, The whole World, all Mankinde muſt take care, that all places be emprou'd, as farre as may be, to the beſt aduantage of Mankind in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</hi> Againe, if the Land be peopled, and cultiuated by the people, and that Land produce in abundance ſuch things, for want whereof, their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or others (being not enemyes) periſh; the Law of <hi>Nations</hi> may iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſome force, in ſeeking, by permu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of other Commodities which they neede, to come to ſome of theirs. Many caſes may be put, when not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Commerce,</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> but <hi>Plantations</hi> in Lands, not formerly our owne, may be lawfull. And for that, <hi>Accepiſtis poteſtatem,</hi> you haue your <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> your <hi>Patents,</hi> your <hi>Charters,</hi> your <hi>Seales</hi> from <hi>Him,</hi> vpon whoſe Acts any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Subiect, in Ciuill matters, may ſafely relye. But then, <hi>Accipietis poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, You ſhall receiue power,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Text;</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:132980:17"/>you ſhall, when the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is come vpon you, that is, when the inſtinct, the influence, the motions of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> enables your Conſcience to ſay, That your principall end is not Gaine, nor Glory, but to gaine Soules to the glory of GOD; this ſeales the Great Seale, this iuſtifies Iuſtice it ſelfe, this authoriſes Authoritie, and giues power to Strength it ſelfe. Let the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be vpright, and then <hi>Seales,</hi> and <hi>Patents,</hi> and <hi>Commiſsions,</hi> are Wings; they aſſiſt him to flye the faſter: Let the Conſcience be lame, and diſtorted, and hee that goes vpon <hi>Seales,</hi> and <hi>Patents,</hi> and <hi>Commiſsions,</hi> goes vpon weake and feeble Crutches. When the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is come vpon you, your Conſcience rectified, you ſhall haue <hi>Power,</hi> a new power out of that; what to doe? that followes, to bee <hi>Witneſſes vnto Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Infamie</hi> is one of the higheſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the Law inflicts vpon man;
<note place="margin">Teſtes.</note>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:132980:17"/>for it lyes vpon him euen after death: <hi>Infamie</hi> is the worſt puniſhment, and <hi>Inteſtabilitie</hi> (to be made <hi>intestable</hi>) is one of the deepeſt wounds of <hi>Infamie;</hi> and then the worſt degree of <hi>intestabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> is not to be beleeued, not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be a Witneſſe of any other: Hee is <hi>Inteſtable,</hi> that cannot make a <hi>Testament,</hi> not giue his owne goods; and hee <hi>Inteſtable,</hi> that can receiue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the <hi>Teſtament</hi> of another; hee is <hi>Inteſtable,</hi> in whoſe behalfe no teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie may be accepted: but be is the moſt miſerably <hi>Intestable</hi> of all, the moſt deteſtably inteſtable, that diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites another man, by ſpeaking well of him; and makes him the more ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious, by his commendations. A <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in profeſſion, that is not a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in life, is ſo inteſtable, hee diſcredites <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and hardens others againſt him. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was more then a <hi>Prophet,</hi> becauſe hee was a <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and hee was a <hi>Witneſſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:132980:18"/>becauſe hee was like him, hee did as hee did, hee lead a holy and a religious life; ſo hee was a <hi>Witneſſe.</hi> That great and glorious name of <hi>Martyr,</hi> is but a <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> was <hi>Proto-martyr, Chriſts</hi> firſt <hi>Witneſſe,</hi> becauſe hee was the firſt that did as hee did, that put on his <hi>Colours,</hi> that drunke of his <hi>Cup,</hi> that was baptiſed with his <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> with his owne <hi>Bloud:</hi> ſo hee was a <hi>Witneſſe.</hi> To be <hi>Witneſſes</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is to be like <hi>Chriſt;</hi> to conforme your ſelues to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and they in the <hi>Text,</hi> and you, are to be <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Chriſt in</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daea, <hi>and in</hi> Samaria, <hi>and vnto the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> notes, that <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> was not bid to beare witneſſe in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jeruſalem.</note> in the <hi>Citie,</hi> but in the <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> hee, and none but hee: there were but few men to witneſſe to, there; and thoſe few that were, came thither with a good diſpoſition, to be wrought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there: and there, there were few
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:132980:18"/>Witneſſes to oppoſe <hi>Iohns</hi> Teſtimonie, few Tentations, few worldly Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, few worldly Buſineſſes. One was enough for the <hi>Wilderneſſe;</hi> but for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> for the <hi>Citie,</hi> where all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> doe alwayes meete, they haue bought Commodities, and they muſt vtter them; they haue du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed Lands, and they muſt ſtate them, they haue married Wiues, and they muſt ſtudie them: to the <hi>Citie,</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem, Chriſt</hi> ſends all his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all little enough. Hee hath ſent a great many <hi>Apoſtles, Preachers,</hi> to this <hi>Citie;</hi> more then to any other, that I know <hi>Religious perſons,</hi> as they call them, <hi>Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered Friars,</hi> are not ſent to the <hi>Citie;</hi> by their firſt <hi>Canons,</hi> they ſhould not preach abroad: but for thoſe who are to doe that ſeruice, there are more in this <hi>Citie,</hi> then in others; for there are more <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> heere, then in others. Now, beloued, if in this <hi>Citie</hi> you haue taken away a great part
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:132980:19"/>of the reuenue of the <hi>Preacher,</hi> to your ſelues, take thus much of his labour vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelues too, as to preach to one another by a holy and exemplar life, and a religious conuerſation. Let thoſe of the <hi>Citie,</hi> who haue intereſt in the Gouernment of this <hi>Plantation,</hi> be <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is <hi>Truth it ſelfe,</hi> to all other <hi>Gouernours</hi> of <hi>Companies,</hi> in all true and iuſt proceedings: That as CHRIST ſaid to them who thought themſelues greateſt, <hi>Except you become as this little Child;</hi> ſo wee may ſay to the <hi>Gouernours</hi> of the greateſt <hi>Companies,</hi> Except you proceed with the integrity, with the iuſtice, with the cleareneſſe of your <hi>little Siſter,</hi> this <hi>Plantation,</hi> you doe not take, you doe not follow a good example. This is to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in the <hi>Citie,</hi> to bee examples of <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Cleareneſſe,</hi> to others, in, and of this <hi>Citie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were to doe this in <hi>Iudaea</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudaea.</note>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:132980:19"/>too, their ſeruice lay in the <hi>Countrey</hi> as well as in the <hi>Citie.</hi> Birds that are kept in Cages, may learne ſome Notes, which they ſhould neuer haue ſung in the Woods, or Fields; but yet they may forget their naturall Notes too. <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> that binde themſelues alwayes to <hi>Cities,</hi> and <hi>Courts,</hi> and <hi>great Auditories,</hi> may learne new Notes; they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>occaſionall</hi> Preachers, and make the emergent affaires of the time, their <hi>Text,</hi> and the humors of the hearers, their <hi>Bible:</hi> but they may loſe their Naturall Notes, both the <hi>ſimplicitie</hi> and the <hi>boldneſſe</hi> that belongs to the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> both their power vpon lowe Vnderſtandings, to rayſe them, and vpon high Affections, to humble them. They may thinke, that their Errand is but to knocke at the doore, to delight the eare, and not to ſearch the Houſe, to ranſacke the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. <hi>Chriſt</hi> left the <hi>Ninetie and nine</hi> for one Sheepe; populous <hi>Cities</hi> are for the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:132980:20"/>moſt part, beſt prouided; remoter parts need our labour more, and wee ſhould not make ſuch differences. <hi>Yeoman,</hi> and <hi>Labourer,</hi> and <hi>Spinſter,</hi> are diſtinctions vpon Earth, in the Earth; in the Graue there is no diſtinction. The <hi>Angell</hi> that ſhall call vs out of that Duſt, will not ſtand to ſuruay, who lyes naked, who in a Coffin, who in Wood, who in Lead; who in a fine, who in a courſer Sheet: In that one day of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, there is not a fore-noone for Lords to riſe firſt, and an after-noone for meaner perſons to riſe after. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not whipp'd, to ſaue Beggars; and crown'd with Thornes, to ſaue Kings; hee dyed, hee ſuffered all, for all: and wee (whoſe bearing witneſſe of him, is to doe as hee did) muſt conferre our Labours vpon all; vpon <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and vpon <hi>Iudaea</hi> too; vpon the <hi>Citie,</hi> and vpon the <hi>Countrey</hi> too. You (who are his Witneſſes too) muſt doe ſo too; Preach in your iuſt actions, as to the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:132980:20"/>
                  <hi>Citie,</hi> to the <hi>Countrey</hi> too. Not to ſeale vp the ſecrets, and the myſteries of your buſineſſe within the boſome of <hi>Merchants,</hi> and exclude all others: to nouriſh an incompatibilitie betweene <hi>Merchants</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentlemen;</hi> that <hi>Merchants</hi> ſhall ſay to them in reproach, You haue playd the <hi>Gentlemen;</hi> and they in equall reproach, You haue playd the <hi>Merchant:</hi> but as <hi>Merchants</hi> grow vp into worſhipfull Families, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Families let fall Branches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Merchants</hi> againe; ſo for this particular Plantation, you may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Citie</hi> and <hi>Countrey</hi> to be one Body: and as you giue example of a iuſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment to other Companies in the <hi>Citie,</hi> (that's your bearing witneſſe in <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi>) ſo you may be content to giue Reaſons of your Proceedings, and Account of Moneyes leuied ouer the <hi>Countrey,</hi> for that's your bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in <hi>Iudaea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:132980:21"/>But the <hi>Apoſtles Dioces</hi> is enlarged, farther then <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> farther then <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Samaria.</note> they are carried into <hi>Samaria; you must beare witneſſe of me in</hi> Samaria. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, when I haue remembred you, who the <hi>Samaritans</hi> were, Men that had not renounced GOD, but mingled other <hi>gods</hi> with him, Men that had not burned the Law of GOD, but made Traditions of Men equall to it; you will eaſily gueſſe to whom I apply the name of <hi>Samaritans</hi> now. A <hi>Ieſuit</hi> hath told vs (an ill Intelligencer I confeſſe, but euen his Intelligencer, the <hi>Deuill</hi> himſelfe, ſayes true ſometimes) <hi>Maldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> ſayes, the <hi>Samaritans</hi> were odious to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> vpon the ſame grounds as <hi>Heretiques</hi> and <hi>Schiſmatiques</hi> to vs; and they we know were odious to them, for mingling falſe <hi>gods,</hi> and falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips with the true. And if that be the Caracter of a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> wee know who are the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques,</hi> who the <hi>Schiſmatiques</hi> of our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:132980:21"/>times. In the higheſt reproach to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Iewes ſaid, <hi>Samaritanus es &amp; Daemonium habes, Thou art a Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and haſt a Deuill.</hi> In our iuſt deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe <hi>Men,</hi> we iuſtly faſten both thoſe vpon them. For as they delight in lyes, and fill the world with weekely rumors, <hi>Daemoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> they haue a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, quia mendax eſt &amp; pater eius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> As they multiply aſſaſſinats vpon Princes, and Maſſacres vpon people, <hi>Daemonium ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent,</hi> they haue a <hi>Deuill, quia homicida ab initio:</hi> as they toſſe, and tumble, and diſpoſe kingdomes, <hi>Daemonium habent,</hi> they haue a <hi>Deuill,
<note place="margin">Math. 4.10.</note> Omnia haec dabo</hi> was the Deuils complement: but as they mingle truthes and falſhoods together in Religion, as they carry the word of GOD, and the Traditions of Men, in an euen balance, <hi>Samaritani ſunt,</hi> they are <hi>Samaritanes.</hi> At firſt <hi>Christ</hi> forbad his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to goe into any Citie of the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> after,
<note place="margin">10.5.</note> they did preach in many of them. Beare witneſſe firſt in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:132980:22"/>
                  <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 8.25.</note> and in <hi>Iudaea;</hi> giue good ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction eſpecially to thoſe of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of the Faithfull, in the <hi>Citie</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> but yet ſatisfie euen thoſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> too.</p>
               <p>They would be ſatisfied, what Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles you work in <hi>Virginia,</hi> and what peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you haue conuerted to the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> there. If wee could as eaſily call natural effects Miracles, or caſuall acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts Miracles, or Magicall illuſions Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, as they do; to make a miraculous drawing of a Tooth, a miraculous cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Corne; or, as <hi>Iuſtus Baronius</hi> ſayes, when he was conuerted to them, that he was miraculouſly cur'd of the <hi>Cholique,</hi> by ſtooping to kiſſe the <hi>Popes</hi> foot: If wee would pile vp Miracles ſo faſt as <hi>Pope Iohn</hi> 22. did in the Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation of <hi>Aquinas, Tot Miracula confecit, quot determinauit quaeſtiones,</hi> hee wrought as many Miracles, as he reſolu'd Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wee might find Miracles too. In truth, their greateſt Miracle to me, is,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:132980:22"/>that they find men to beleeue their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles. If they rely vpon Miracles, they imply a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion, that they induce new Doctrines; that that is old, &amp; receiu'd, needs no Miracles: If they require Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, becauſe though that be ancient Doctrine, it is newly brought into thoſe parts, wee haue the confeſſion of their Ieſuit <hi>Acoſta,</hi> that they doe no Miracle in thoſe <hi>Indies;</hi> &amp; he aſſignes very good reaſons, why they are not neceſſary, nor to be expected there. But yet beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to theſe <hi>Samaritans,</hi> in the other point; labour to giue them ſatisfaction in the other point of their charge, What Heathens you haue conuerted to the Faith; which is that which is intended in the next, which is the laſt branch, <hi>You are to be witneſſes vnto me both in</hi> Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Iudaea, <hi>and in</hi> Samaria, <hi>and vnto the vttermoſt parts of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Literally,
<note place="margin">Fines terrae.</note> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were to be ſuch Witneſſes for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> were they ſo? did the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in perſon preach the <hi>Goſpel</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:132980:23"/>ouer all the World? I know that it is not hard to multiply places of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> in confirmation of that opinion, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did actually and perſonally preach the <hi>Goſpell</hi> in all Nations,
<note place="margin">Math. 24.14.</note> in their life. <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaies, <hi>The Goſpell of the Kingdome ſhall be preached in all the World;</hi> and there he tels the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> that they ſhall ſee ſomething done, after that; Therefore they ſhall liue to it. So hee ſaies to them,
<note place="margin">Marke 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>You ſhall be brought before Rulers and Kings for my ſake;</hi> but the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell</hi> muſt firſt be publiſhed among all Nations: In one <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> there is the <hi>Commiſsion;
<note place="margin">Luke 24.47.</note> Preach in my name to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> And in another, the <hi>Execution</hi> of this <hi>Commiſsion,
<note place="margin">Marke 16.20.</note> And they went and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched euery where.</hi> And after the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> certifies, and returnes the execution of this Commiſſion,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>The Goſpell is come and bringeth forth fruit to all the world:</hi> and vpon thoſe, and ſuch places, haue ſome of the <hi>Fathers</hi> beene pleaſed to ground their literall expoſition, of an actuall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:132980:23"/>and perſonall preaching of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ouer all the world. But had they dream'd of this world which hath beene diſcouer'd ſince, into which, we diſpute with perplexitie, and intricacy enough, how any men came at firſt, or how any beaſts, eſpecially ſuch beaſts as men were not likely to carry, they would neuer haue doubted to haue admitted a <hi>Figure,</hi> in that,
<note place="margin">Luke 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>The Goſpell was preached to all the world;</hi> for when <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his Decree went out, <hi>That all the World ſhould bee taxed,</hi> the Decree and the Taxe went not certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the <hi>West Indies;</hi> when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes,
<note place="margin">Rom 1.8.16.19.</note> 
                  <hi>That their Faith was ſpoken of throughout the whole World,</hi> and that <hi>their obedience was come abroad vnto all men,</hi> ſurely the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> had not heard of the <hi>faith</hi> and the <hi>obedience</hi> of the <hi>Romanes.</hi> But as in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, they called the <hi>Mediterranean Sea,</hi> the <hi>great Sea,</hi> becauſe it was the greateſt that thoſe men had then ſeene, ſo in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:132980:24"/>
                  <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, they call'd that all the World, which was knowne and traded in then; and in all that, they preach'd the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> So that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> when hee ſaid to the <hi>Apoſtles;
<note place="margin">Mar. vlt. vlt.</note> I am with you vnto the end of the World,</hi> could not intend that of them in perſon, becauſe they did not laſt to the end of the World, but in a ſucceſſion of Apoſtolike men, ſo when he ſayes, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſhould preach him to all the World, it is of the <hi>Succeſsion</hi> too.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of our profeſſion, that goe; you, that ſend them who goe, doe all an <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> Function. What Action ſoeuer hath in the firſt intention there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a purpoſe to propagate the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> that is an <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> Action: Before the end of the World come, before this Mortalitie ſhall put on Immortalitie,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> before the Creature ſhall be deliuered of the Bondage of Corruption vnder which it groanes, before the Martyrs vnder the Altar
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:132980:24"/>ſhall be ſilenc'd, before all things ſhall be ſubdued to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his Kingdome perfited, and the laſt Enemie (Death) deſtroyed, the Goſpell muſt be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to thoſe men to whom ye ſend, to all men. Further and haſten you this bleſſed, this ioyfull, this glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of all, and happie re-vnion of all Bodies to their Soules, by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Goſpell</hi> to thoſe men. Preach to them <hi>Doctrinally,</hi> preach to them <hi>Practically;</hi> enamore them with your <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and (as farre as may conſiſt with your ſecuritie) your <hi>Ciuilitie;</hi> but inflame them with your <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> and your <hi>Religion.</hi> Bring them to <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>reuerence</hi> the name of that <hi>King,</hi> that ſends men to teach them the wayes of <hi>Ciuilitie</hi> in this World, but to <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>adore</hi> the Name of that <hi>King of Kings,</hi> that ſends men to teach them the wayes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for the next World. Thoſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you, that are old now, ſhall paſſe out of this World with this great comfort,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:132980:25"/>that you contributed to the beginning of that Common Wealth, and of that Church, though they liue not to ſee the growth thereof to perfection: <hi>Apollo</hi> watred,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.6.</note> but <hi>Paul</hi> planted; he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun the worke, was the greater man. And you that are young now, may liue to ſee the Enemy as much impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by that place, and your friends, yea Children, aſwell accommodated in that place, as any other. You ſhall haue made this <hi>Iland,</hi> which is but as the <hi>Suburbs</hi> of the old world, a Bridge, a Gallery to the new; to ioyne all to that world that ſhall neuer grow old, the Kingdome of Heauen, You ſhall adde perſons to this Kingdome, and to the Kingdome of Heauen, and adde names to the Bookes of our Chronicles, and to the Booke of Life.</p>
               <p>To end all, as the <hi>Orators</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in the preſence of the <hi>Roman Emperors,</hi> in their <hi>Panegyriques,</hi> tooke that way, to make thoſe <hi>Emperours</hi> ſee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:132980:25"/>what they were bound to doe, to ſay in thoſe publique Orations, that thoſe <hi>Emperors</hi> had done ſo, (for that increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the loue of the Subiect to the Prince, to be ſo told, that he had done thoſe great things, and then it conuayd a Counſell into the Prince to doe them after.) As their way was to procure things to be done, by ſaying they were done, ſo beloued I haue taken a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary way: for when I, by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, all this while haue ſeemed to tell you what ſhould be done by you; I haue, indeed, but told the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, what hath beene done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: neither doe I ſpeake to moue a wheele that ſtood ſtill, but to keepe the wheele in due motion; nor perſwade you to begin, but to continue a good worke; nor propoſe forreigne, but your owne Examples, to doe ſtill, as you haue done hitherto. For, for that, that which is eſpecially in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, the conuerſion of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:132980:26"/>people, as I haue receiu'd, ſo I can giue this Teſtimonie, That of thoſe perſons who haue ſent in Moneyes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd their Names, the greateſt part, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all, haue limitted their Deuotion and Contribution vpon that point, the propagation of Religion, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the People; for the building and beautifying of the Houſe of GOD, and for the inſtruction and education of their young Children. <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe <hi>is yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for euer.</hi> In the aduancing of his Glory, be you ſo too, yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for euer, here: and hereafter, when Time ſhall be no more, no more yeſterday, no more to day, yet for euer and euer you ſhall enioy that ioy, and that glorie, which no ill acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent can attayne to diminiſh, or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:132980:26"/>
               <head>PRAYER.</head>
               <p>WE returne to thee againe, O GOD, with <hi>Prayſe</hi> and <hi>Prayer;</hi> as for all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from before Minutes began, to this Minute; from our Election, to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Beame of Sanctification, which thou haſt ſhed vpon vs now: and more particularly, that thou haſt afforded vs that great Dignitie, to be this way Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of thy Sonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his Glorie. Looke graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and looke powerfully vpon this Body, which thou haſt been now ſome yeeres in building and compacting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, this Plantation. Looke graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vpon the Head of this Body, our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and bleſſe him with a good diſpoſition to this Worke, and bleſſe him for that diſpoſition: Looke graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vpon them, who are as the <hi>Braine</hi> of this Body, thoſe who by his power
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:132980:27"/>counſaile, and aduiſe, and aſſiſt in the Gouernment thereof: bleſſe them with diſpoſition to Vnitie and Concord, and bleſſe them for that diſpoſition. Looke graciouſly vpon them who are as <hi>Eyes</hi> of this Body, thoſe of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> who haue any intereſt therein: bleſſe them with a diſpoſition to preach there, to pray here, to exhort euery where, for the aduancement thereof, and bleſſe them for that diſpoſition. Bleſſe them who are the <hi>Feet</hi> of this Body, who goe thither; and the <hi>Hands</hi> of this Bodie, who labour there; and them who are the <hi>Heart</hi> of this Body; all that are hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily affected, and declare actually that heartineſſe to this action; bleſſe them all with a cheereful diſpoſition to that, and bleſſe them for that diſpoſition. Bleſſe it ſo in this Calme, that when the Tempeſt comes, it may ride it out ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; bleſſe it ſo with Friends now, that it may ſtand againſt Enemies hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Prepare thy ſelfe a glorious Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:132980:27"/>there, and giue vs leaue to be thy Labourers, That ſo the number of thy <hi>Saints</hi> being fulfilled, wee may with better aſſurance ioyne in that Prayer, <hi>Come Lord Ieſus, come quickly;</hi> and ſo meet all in that Kingdome which the Sonne of GOD hath purchaſed for vs with the ineſtimable price of his incorruptible Bloud. To which glorious Sonne of GOD, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
